Perilous winds
and unsettling new lands
take their toll on the voyagers
who now explore
a small island, rich in gold.
Is this part of
the plan, Lord Odysseus?
Indeed, Eurylochus.
Now stay close,
and your lips closed.
I don’t quite understand
what this has to do with gold.
We’re going to retrieve gold.
My gold that was
stolen by a cyclops.
He’s the son of Poseidon,
God of the sea.
A real cyclops?
Why didn’t you tell us sooner?
They eat people, so I’ve heard.
My brave crew...
Alkimos, you wanted adventure.
Here it is.
Eurylochus, you wanted to stay
alive in a cave with a Cyclops.
You must learn to be faster.
And Polites,
now you wanted gold.
Yes, this cyclops has
been hoarding gold for years.
Mine and others.
And that gold will
help me pay your rewards.
He’s been terrorizing this
mountainside for many years.
It’s time we return the favor.
Today, our journey
begins with a cyclops.
Or it ends before it begins.
Now who’s with me?
My king.
Help! Help!
He... He ate him.
Do as I say when I say,
then we will win the day.
All right, what’s the plan?
We’ll circle the
base of the mountain.
Go inside.
Stay close, and downwind.
Cyclops, he can smell
us nearly a league away.
Hold, hold, hold.
At Troy, during the
war, you were there?
I sure was.
I barely survived,
and I probably wouldn’t have
if it weren’t for Odysseus.
Saved me from
an entire garrison.
Picked them off one by one.
Hiding in the shadows,
which is a pretty big
feat for him, considering
he’s a big bastard.
I’ve only heard stories.
Legends, really.
Well, not everything
you hear is true.
Only half of what
I just said was true.
Is he as good a man as they say?
He’s a great man, though
he’d never admit it.
But out of humility.
He’s a man who
values many virtues.
But the one he values above
all others is cleverness.
You see, a good man engenders
himself to friends, family.
A clever man,
a clever man survives.
Quickly, now.
Gods willing, we will, too.
Keep your eyes open and
your wits about you, man.
Odysseus, you know
no-ones actually entered
the Cyclops cave and
lived to tell the tale.
Not until today they don’t.
He will be busy
with his guest.
This is our chance.
We sneak in,
find the treasure,
take what we can carry,
stay quiet,
get out the same way.
Stay with me.
Stay low.
But how do we find the treasure?
Where does the cyclops
even keep its treasure?
It smells like death.
What better place to
hide your gold than in
a place that smells so bad
that no one dares enter?
Use your nose.
Follow its direction.
Is... Is somebody here?
I smell...
I smell men.
I smell your fear.
You can’t...
You can’t hide for long
and Polyphemus,
the son of Poseidon,
is still hungry.
There.
The smell of the
worst is that way.
Move, move.
Let’s move.
Quiet.
Holy gold.
Reward.
Rewards for good men.
Shh.
Okay, quickly.
Take everything you can.
Actually, only what you can
carry, just like Odysseus said.
Wait, where is Odysseus?
Odysseus is gone.
You’ve come for my gold!
Shh!
- Thieves!
- Okay, take cover!
Thieves, who are you?
We’re nobody!
Grab the treasure! Run!
Go! I’ll keep him busy!
We fight with you,
my king!
Eurylochus!
Odysseus!
Polites, help! Ah!
No! No!
You will die, foul beast!
For Eurylochus!
Nobody?
It calls for help.
No one will come!
It calls out for nobody.
No one will come.
May the gods bless
you, Eurylochus,
and speed you
through the underworld
as quickly as
the gods will permit.
Now, go.
Grab the treasure.
The son of Poseidon will
not lick his wounds long.
Go!
- Only take what we need.
Yes, enough for a boat.
Provisions and no more.
Okay, here’s a bit of gold.
There’s a bit of this...
- Hurry!
- Yes, grab that.
That’s expensive, I like that.
Okay, and...
Yes, let’s go.
Go, go!
Charie!
And greetings to the
great house of Odysseus.
Greetings to you, traveler.
Your voice seems so...
familiar.
But our house is
in no condition...
Aye, aye.
Well met, my lord Telelachus.
Telemachus.
Apologies. Apologies.
I am Antinous.
And I come bearing gifts.
The gift of my protection.
A gracious home.
A kingly estate, indeed.
Ready our ship, men.
We leave port immediately.
- My king.
Come to wish us farewell?
I have.
And I come bearing a gift.
A bag of wind
to speed you along your journey.
Perhaps if you’d
accepted my offer of help,
and asked for stronger
and faster ships,
you would not need it.
Or you would already
be closer to home.
My ship.
I would not trust
a boat from the gods.
Who knows if the previous owners
seek revenge and come find me?
And what of the previous
owners of this treasure?
My ship.
My treasure.
My men.
What’s left of them.
By Olympus.
One of the gods
speaking to Odysseus.
Gifts.
Gifts from the gods themselves.
It’s a generous gift.
And I accept your bag of wind.
But it is not one of your
three gifts until I use it.
Why not use it now?
I will use it.
But I will use it when I must.
The gifts of a god
come with a heavy price.
Hurry home, son of Laertes.
Honor me.
Rewards.
Odysseus!
Was that...
Athena herself.
Come to wish us a farewell.
Could she help us?
Help us get there faster.
I would give my life
many times over if it
meant getting home
sooner to my loved ones.
But the gods play
dangerous games with men.
They could spirit us home
with just a mere thought.
Or the breath from their lungs.
Or they could smite us where we
stand and send us to our dooms.
To them, it’s all the same.
That’s why we
must tread lightly.
Especially with the ones
who seem the most generous.
And what of that?
Is that a gift?
A reward?
No, it’s nothing.
It’s a good luck charm.
Now, Polites, let’s go home.
A guest in my home.
Aye, but not just any guest.
Antinous, my queen.
At your service.
Well met, Antinous.
And to what do we
owe this generous visit?
I come to pay my respects
to the great Odysseus himself.
And to those he left behind.
He will return. He...
And we accept that respect
in the spirit
that it was given.
Thank you, Antinous.
And I am here to confirm
that this home is safe.
Safe from any who might think
to encroach upon its sanctity.
And to offer my
allegiance and my duty to you
and yours
and to this kingdom.
And to offer my services
to you
as husband and father...
and king.
There is no need for that.
Or for you. My father--
You’ll forgive my son.
He can be rather spirited.
Much like his father.
A generous proposal, indeed.
But we have only just met.
Perhaps we can get
better acquainted first.
A fair suggestion.
Right and good.
But I have to admit,
my gracious queen.
I am famished.
And my lips are parched from
my long journey to your door.
Yes. Refreshments might
do us all some good.
Telemachus.
I could use your help.
Take your time.
I’m in no rush.
Mother, what are you doing?
My duty, my son.
And I expect you to do the same.
Antinous is our guest.
Antinous is a
lecherous fool who...
Mother, I--
There will be
other fools, son.
He is merely the first.
It’s just like I warned you.
Every day Ithaca
goes without a king
and our house without
our dearest love,
we edge closer
and closer to chaos.
While he is here, the others in
waiting will keep
their distance.
Concerned about their chances,
making assumptions...
Peace is kept.
But mother, I don’t think...
We keep--
We keep him distracted.
And we buy your father time.
And while we wait
and be polite and
kowtow to that,
any peace we buy
is not guaranteed.
It is all we can do.
For now.
Now, come on.
We mustn’t keep our
honored guest waiting.
Steady there, Alkimos.
With any luck, we’ll be home
in a day and a half.
My king.
A storm’s coming.
Keep it steady, Alkimos.
Put your back into it.
Polites, grab those lines.
We’re going to need them.
Poseidon’s bad breath.
Poseidon’s breath?
Hot air and spit.
That’s Poseidon’s bad breath.
He must have learned of
the mark I left on his son.
And his ocean is
pushing us off course.
Look, there.
Oh, yes.
The current.
It turns against us.
Yes.
Adjust your heading.
Into the wind.
- The wind?
- Yes.
My king...
Poseidon’s strength is strongest
in the water and the current.
But if we catch the wind
we can use it as our guide.
Polites, fortify the mast
and the sail.
We cannot afford to be
any further from our goal.
My king, the ship...
She can’t hold it.
She will do what
we tell her to do.
The wind going one way
and the current the other.
I’m afraid we’re
going to be torn apart.
If we catch the wind,
tread lightly.
We can crest the waves
instead of wrestling with them.
Yes.
We must tread lightly if we
want to keep pace with those.
Spit all you want, Poseidon!
I will not be swayed.
Not today, not ever.
Odysseus...
The waves!
The waves, they’re coming
right for us.
We’ve got
to keep her on course!
Try harder.
Come on!
Come on, oh gods. Punish me!
Punish me!
The sea,
she means to turn us over!
- Odysseus.
- Hold tight.
Hold tight, men.
We can steer her.
We’re not strong enough.
We’re not going to make it.
The sea shall eat us all.
The wind.
The wind’s too strong.
We’re going to lose the sail.
No. No, it’s not too strong.
It’s the strength we need.
Hand me those lines.
Pull the oar.
Pull with all your might!
Pull!
If we lose the oar,
we’re done for.
If we do not act now, we die.
Pull the oar!
Pull it!
That’s it. That’s it!
The wind is the
strength we need.
It’s working.
Odysseus.
Wind.
Wind and water.
They are nothing.
They are nothing
when Ithaca waits for us.
I’m coming home.
I am coming home.
So then...
Queen Penelope.
Antinous.
Do you have need of more food?
Or drink perhaps?
Both. Please.
Your wine.
It has a lovely bouquet.
A noble vintage indeed.
A captivating aroma.
And sweet acidity.
It is rich.
And full bodied.
Just like you.
You do flatter me, Antinous.
Maybe I do.
But...
I worry...
The time for flattery
has passed.
There will be other suitors
lining up at your door.
And soon...
They will be much
less patient men than I.
And after the suitors